Register of the Vladimir N. Ipatieff Papers, 1896-1953
Hoover Institution Archives
- Vladimir N. Ipatieff papers in the Museum of Russian Culture (Reel 1-7)
  - Speeches And Writings, 1891-1952.
    - "Hydrogénation catalytique sous pression du paraoxytriphénylcarbinol et du paraoxydiphénylméthane," Comptes-rendus de l'Académie des Sciences, Negative photostat, 1928. (Folder 16)
    - "Die Kondensation von Oxy-säuren durch gleichzeitige Einwirkung mehrerer Katalysatoren unter hohem Wasserstoff-Druck; a-Oxy- n-buttersäure und a-Oxy-isovaleriansäure," Berichte der deutschen chemischen Gesellschaft, Negative photostat, 1928. (Folder 17)
    - "Sur la rupture de quelques dérivés des naphtylméthanes pendant l'hydrogénation sous pression," Bulletin de la Société Chimique de France, Negative photostat, 1928. (Folder 18)
    - "Die Einwirkung von Ammoniak auf halogen-substituirte Arsine," Berichte der deutschen chemischen Gesellschaft, Negative photostat, 1929. (Folder 19)
    - "Les pétroles artificiels," Chaleur et industrie, Negative photostat, 1929. (Folder 20)
    - "Pyrogenetische Zersetzung aromatischer Verbindungen unter Wasserstoff-Druck bei Gegenwart eines gemischten Katalysators (II. Mitteilung)," Berichte der deutschen chemischen Gesellschaft, Negative photostat, 1929. (Folder 21)
    - "Recherches sur les combustibles liquides," Chimie et industrie, Negative photostat, 1929. (Folder 22)
    - "Verdrängung von Kupfer aus neutralen und sauren Kupfersulfat-Lösungen durch Wasserstoff unter Druck," Berichte der deutschen chemischen Gesellschaft, Negative photostat, 1929. (Folder 23)
    - "Über Hydrierung und Zerfall von silicium-organischen Verbindungen bei hohen Temperaturen und Drucken (Vorläfige Mitteilung)," Berichte der deutschen chemischen Gesellschaft, Negative photostat, 1929. (Folder 24)
    - "Über pyrogenetische Zersetzung von Holzteer in Gegenwart von Wasserstoff und unter Druck," Berichte der deutschen chemischen Gesellschaft, Negative photostat, 1929. (Folder 25)
    - "Verdrängung von Metallen und ihren Oxyden durch Wasserstoff unter Druck bei hohen Temperaturen," Berichte der deutschen chemischen Gesellschaft, Negative photostat. Includes "Einwirkung von Wasserstoff bei hohen Drucken und Temperaturen auf Lösungen von Rutheniumsalzen" (ibid.), 1929. (Folder 26)
    - "Cracken der Urteers aus einer Kohle des Donez-Reviers unter Wasserstoff-Druck," Berichte der deutschen chemischen Gesellschaft, Negative photostat, 1930. (Folder 27)
    - "Druck-Erhitzung von Naphthensäuren," Berichte der deutschen chemischen Gesellschaft, Negative photostat, 1930. (Folder 28)
    - "Einwirkung von Wasserstoff auf metallorganische Verbindungen unter hohen Druck," Berichte der deutschen chemischen Gesellschaft, Negative photostat, 1930. (Folder 29)
    - "Synthese des [a-Chlor-styryl]-dichlor-arsins," Berichte der deutschen chemischen Gesellschaft, Negative photostat, 1930. (Folder 30)
    - "Die Verdrängung der Elemente der 5. Gruppe aus ihren Phenyl-Derivaten durch Wasserstoff," Berichte der deutschen chemischen Gesellschaft, Negative photostat, 1930. (Folder 31)
    - "Verdrängung der Metalle aus den Lösungen ihrer Salze durch Wasserstoff unter hohen Temperaturen und Drucken," Berichte der deutschen chemischen Gesellschaft, Negative photostat. Includes "Verdrängung des Arsens aus seinen Salzun durch Wasserstoff" (ibid.), 1930. (Folder 32)
    - "Verdrängung von Metallen und ihren Oxyden aus den Lösungen ihrer Salze durch Wasserstoff bei hohen Temperaturen und Drucken," Berichte der deutschen chemischen Gesellschaft, Negative photostat. Includes "Die Einwirkung des Wasserstoffs auf Metallnitrate" (ibid.), 1930. (Folder 33)
    - "Elektroliz vody pod davleniem," 15-oi godovshchine oktiabria, Printed copy. Article officially authored by V. V. Shishkin, but autograph of Ipatieff opens possibility of his authorship (at least jointly). Also includes two articles by Ipatieff's son, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1932. (Folder 34)
    - "Gidrogenizatsiia pri vysokikh temperaturakh i davleniiakh," Typescript, 1935 January 2. (Folder 35)
    - "Phosphoric Acid as the Catalyst for Alkylation of Aromatic Hydrocarbons," Industrial and Engineering Chemistry, 1936 February. Printed copy. Includes "Phosphoric Acid as a Catalyst for the Destructive Alkylation of Hydrocarbons," The Journal of the American Chemical Society, Printed copy (Folder 36)
    - "The Problem of the Rational Utilization of Petroleum and Petroleum Distillates," Oil and Gas Journal, Printed copy, 1936 November 11. (Folder 37)
    - "Catalysis - The Chemistry of the Future," The Chemical Bulletin, Printed copy. Includes biographical information on Ipatieff later in same issue, 1937 December. (Folder 38)
    - "Nove katalitichke metode za sintezu ugliovodonika," Glasnik Khemiskog Drushtva Kralievine Jugoslavije, Printed copy, 1938. (Folder 39)
    - "Catalytic Refining Methods," The Oil and Gas Journal, Printed copy, 1939 March 30. (Folder 40)
    - "Opit za izuchavane aktivnost'ta na smieseni katalizatori i prilozhenie na emanatsionnata metoda," Khimiia i industriia, Printed copy, 1939 October. (Folder 41)
    - "Aviation Gasoline by Polymerization and Alkylation of Cracking Gases," Chemical and Engineering News, Typescript and printed copy, 1942 November 10. (Folder 42)
    - "Modern Science in Russia," Journal of Chemical Education, Printed copy, 1943 April. (Folder 43)
    - Zhizn' odnogo khimika, 1945
      - Typescript (volume II only) (Folder 44)
      - Printed copy (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - English edition, The Life of a Chemist, Printed copy, 1946. (Folder 2)
      - Reviews. See OVERSIZE FILE/Scrapbooks
    - "Moi vospominaniia ob otkrytii reaktsii vytiesneniia metallov iz vodnykh rastvorov ikh solei vodorodom pod davleniem i pri vysokoi temperaturie," Typescript, 1952 July 5. (Folder 3)
    - Miscellany. Partial index to scientific articles (Folder 4)
  - Patents, 1934-1947
    Arranged chronologically
    - 1934-1936 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - 1937-1941 (Folder 2)
    - 1942-1943 (Folder 3)
    - 1944-1945 (Folder 4)
    - 1946-1947 (Folder 5)
  - Photographs, n.d.
    Two photographs relating to Ipatieff's scientific work
    - Two photographs - one of a sketch of a catalytic tree modeled on Ipatieff's work, and the other of the growth of metallic crystals. For photos of Ipatieff, see BIOGRAPHICAL FILE (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Oversize File, 1937-1953
    Addresses honoring Ipatieff and scrapbooks of biographical information on him
    - Scrapbooks
      - Condolences and obituaries on Ipatieff's death, Includes Ipatieff's article, "Moia vera," n.d. (clipping from unidentified newspaper), 1952-1953. (Box 7, Oversize 2)
      - Information on Ipatieff's scientific discoveries and achievements. Includes his Mixed Catalysts, 1940 May 24 (printed copy). Also includes abridged version published in Science, 1940 June 28 (Box 8, Oversize 1)
      - Reminiscences and biographical sketches of Ipatieff written by others, clippings from newspapers mentioning him, and reviews of his autobiography, Zhizn' odnogo khimika (Oversize 2)
    - Addresses honoring Ipatieff. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE (Oversize 3)